Guide to the Vassar College Dean of Students Records, 1877-2003 (bulk 1887-1992)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Vassar College Dean of Students Records
1877-2003
1877-1992
Vassar College. Dean of Students
8.2 cubic feet (9 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Materials relating to student life, campus facilities, admissions, events, as well as other student life and general administrative issues.
Administrative History
The current Office of the Dean of Students "oversees and coordinates the Office of Residential Life, Counseling Service, Health Services, International Services and the array of faculty, administrative, and student personnel who assist in the residence halls... In addition, the dean supervises the student fellow program—recruiting, training, and coordinating the activities of student fellows." Although the name has changed several times, the office was created at the founding of the college. The Lady Principal was the first college official to deal with student life and the rules and regulations of the college. The initial charge of the principal was ensure that students personal, moral and spiritual needs were being tended. She acted as an academic and personal advisor, oversaw student housing, and presided over most social events. The responsibilities of the office have changed in the succeeding decades, but the main focus is still student life.
Chronology of Office Names
1865-1913 Lady Principal
1913-1963 Warden
1963-1969 Dean of Residence
1969-1980s Vice President for Student Affairs
1980s-1991 Vice President for Administrative and Student Affairs
1991-1995 Dean of Student Life
1995-present Dean of Students
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, minutes, questionnaires, blueprints and architectural drawings relating to student life, campus facilities, admissions, events, as well as other student life and general administrative issues. The records contain much information about changes in student regulations and the concept of in loco parentis.
Access
Boxes 7 and 8 contain records restricted to the office of origin due to student and personnel privacy issues. The rest of the collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
See also the Lady Principal records in the
Vassar College Archives Files
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College--Students; Vassar College--Administration; Vassar College--Buildings
Subjects:
Women's colleges--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Women college students--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; College discipline
Document Types:
Blueprints; Architectural drawings
VCL Categories
Vassar College Administrative Offices and Functions
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, July 2009.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Dean of Students office and its predecessors in several accessions.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 4 series. The first 3 are based loosely on the various titles of the office, although there is much overlap. The fourth is a 2014 accession of material on the House Fellow program.
Series List
- Series I. Mixed Records, 1877-1979; (Boxes 1-4)
  The Mixed Records series includes materials from the offices of the Lady Principal, the Warden, the Dean of Residence, and the Vice President for Student Affairs.
- Series II. Vice President for Student Affairs, 1970-1980; (Box 5)
  Materials relating to the duties of the Vice President that related to admissions.
- Series III. Vice President for Administrative and Student Affairs, 1966-1992; (Boxes 5-6)
  Subject files kept by the VP for Administrative and Student Affairs, although some materials date to earlier incarnations of the office.
- Series IV. House Fellow Program, 1951-2003; (Boxes 7-9)
  Materials documenting the founding and growth of the House Fellow Program.
  See also, the folders in boxes 2 and 6, which contain material dating from 1947-1959 and 1978-1989.
  Please note that the bulk of material dating after 1961 is currently restricted.
Container List
- SERIES I. Mixed Records
  - Lady Principal's record books, 1877-1891; (9 volumes) (Box 1)
  - Lady Principal's calendar and expense book, 1891-1915; (1 volume) (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Teacher's Meetings, 1883-1884; (1 volume) (Box 1)
  - Absence record books, ca. 1903-1909; (2 volumes) (Box 1)
  - Warden's Calendar, 1915-1921; (1 volume) (Box 1)
  - Warden's Meeting notes, 1915-1931; (4 folders holding multiple bundles) (Box 1)
  - Registration books, 1924-1948; (3 volumes) (Box 1)
  - Room draw records, ca. 1912-1919; (1 volume and 1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous alphabetical records, ca. 1914-1924; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Warden - Plan of Work, ca. 1923-1947; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Warden - Speeches, 1938, 1953, n.d.; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Lathrop Plan (Student Waitresses), ca. 1942; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Student-Faculty Joint Committee, 1935-1939; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Conferences - A.S.U., Dec 1938; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Conferences - World Youth Congress, 1938; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - World War II, (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Three-Year Plan, (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Trustee Information Requests, 1959-1962; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous - Mail, Locks, etc., 1938-1950; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Riding, Sailing and Flying, 1955; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Food Service, 1951; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Language Corridors, 1945-1948; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Kenyon Hall, 1934-1955; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Mental Hygiene, 1941-1948; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Radio Station, 1948-1949; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Parlors, 1943-1944; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Outing Club, 1939-1955; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Marriage Courses and Married Students, 1934-1944; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Student Expenditures, 1925-1949; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1967, 1973, 1975; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Special Committee on Sarah Gibson Blanding's retirement, 1963-1964; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Trustee Committee on Women, 1971-1972; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Administrative Retreat, 1949-1965; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Alumnae - Complaints, 1961; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Faculty Committee on Student Affairs, 1968-1969; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Coeducation, 1967-1970; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Coeducation - Protest letters, 1969-1971; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Student governance, ca. 1950-1967; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Student participation in governance, 1965-1969; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - The [black student] sit-in, 1969; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Senior privileges, 1966-1967; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Underclass and senior regulations, 1968; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Social regulations, 1969; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Revisions of social regulations, 1969; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - College regulations, 1969; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Financial policies re student organizations, 1940-1959; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Student organizations - Annual balances, 1941-1960; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - House fellow plan, 1947-1951; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - House fellows, 1957-1959; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Cooperative houses, ca. 1933-1940; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Cooperative system, 1951-1952; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Ferry House, 1950-1967; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - French House, 1968-1969; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Kendrick House, 1967-1969; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Drugs, 1972; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Alcohol, 1971; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Student organizations - policies, 1967-1970; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Student elections - Procedures and results, 1967-1968; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - College Government Association, 1968-1969; (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Student Government Association, 1970-1972; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Founder's Day Reports, 1950-1957; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Founder's Day, 1969-1976; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - Commencement notes, 1935-1958; (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Daisy chains, academic processions, 1951-1959; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Film: "The Mirror,", 1960; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous reports, etc., on freshmen, etc., (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Master Planning Committee?, ca. 1965; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Master Planning Committee, 1969-1974; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Master Planning Committee - Townhouses, 1969-1971; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Master Planning Sub-Committee - Student Housing, 1971-1972; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Master Planning Committee - Vassar Farm, 1975-1976; (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Townhouses, 1968-1971; (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Dormitories, 1967; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Dormitory Committee Minutes, 1967-1968; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Articles on residences, 1967; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Pre-fab dormitories, 1968; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Dormitories - questionnaire, 1967; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Dormitories - Storage requirements, ca. 1967; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Vassar Dormitory Rehab Study, 1972; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Released space, 1973; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Dormitories, ca. 1973; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - New dormitory, 1971; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Dining - center, 1970-1971; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Terrace Apartments, 1972; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Terrace Apartments - Committee on Furnishings, 1972; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Dormitories - Suggestions, 1968; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - New Housing, 1972; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Variable room rents, 1972; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Room alterations, 1973-1974; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Emergency room assignments, 1975-1976; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Students' building, 1946-1964; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Students' building - Child room, 1971-1974; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous building plans and files, some from the Master Planning Committee, ca. 1965-1979; (several folders and loose plans) (Box 4)
  - Recommendation letters — RESTRICTED FILES, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Student status and leaves — RESTRICTED FILES, (3 folders) (Box 7)
- SERIES II. Vice President for Student Affairs
  - Admissions — Common application, 1976; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Admissions — Director of Admissions, 1974-1976; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Admissions — HEW Investigation of Discrimination, 1973-1975; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Admissions — Minority Recruitment, 1970-1982; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Admissions — Publications, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Admissions — Recruiting film, 1974; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Admissions — Statistics, 1968-1980; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Admissions — Studies, (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Admissions — Admissions Study Report, 1974; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Admissions — Vassar Alumnae Admissions Handbook, 1976; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Admissions — RESTRICTED FILES, (12 folders) (Box 7)
- SERIES III. Vice President for Administrative and Student Affairs
  - Auxiliary Services, 1981-1991; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Auxiliary Services — RESTRICTED FILES, (1 folder) (Box 7)
  - Budget Requests — Auxiliary Services, 1989-1992; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Budget Requests — Food, 1989-1992; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Budget Requests — Halls, 1990-1992; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Budget Requests — Security, 1989-1992; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Campus Activities — Administration, 1973-1983; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Campus Activities — Alcoholic Beverage Catering - Revised Liquor Regulations, 1976-1989; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Campus Activities — College Center, 1975-1989; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Campus Activities — Convocation, Commencement, etc., 1985-1989; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Campus Activities — Social Life, 1986-1987; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Campus Activities — Transportation, 1973-1974; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Campus Activities — Use of Buildings, 1972-1989; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Campus Activities — Video Yearbook, 1986-1987; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Chess Club, 1980-1981; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Coeducation — Inquiries, 1969-1987; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Coeducation — Intracollege Correspondence and Notes, 1967-1984; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Coeducation — Reports from other Colleges, 1973-1977; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Coeducation — Studies and News Articles, 1966-1974; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Confidentiality — RESTRICTED FILES, (1 folder) (Box 7)
  - Council of International Exchange of Scholars, 1984; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Demonstrations, 1969; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Drugs and Alcohol, 1988-1991; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Facilities Operations, 1989-1991; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - Facilities Resources Management Report on Vassar's "Facilities Financial Exposure,", 1986; (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - FIPSE Application, ca. 1990; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Food Service Security — Food Service, 1989-1991; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Food Service Security — ARA, 1983-1990; (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Food Service Security — Before ARA, 1982-1991; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Forms, ca. 1986; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Freshman Orientation, 1978-1989; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Freshman Parents Weekend, 1982-1984; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Halls, 1983-1991; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Halls — RESTRICTED FILES, (1 folder) (Box 7)
  - Housing Procedures and Policies, ca.1986; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - I.D. Committee, 1989-1990; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Health Services, 1988; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - House Fellows, 1978-1989; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Mug — RESTRICTED FILES, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - New York State Department of Education, 1989-1990; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Noyes West End Coffee House, 1982-1986; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Parents — RESTRICTED FILES, (1 folder) (Box 7)
  - Radio Station, 1980-1989; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Rumors and Clarifications, 1990-1991; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Schwartz Fund — RESTRICTED FILES, (1 folder) (Box 7)
  - Security — General, ca. 1979-1986; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Security — Advisory Committee, 1980-1991; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Security — Campus Patrol, 1989-1991; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Security — Consultants, ca. 1987-1990; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Security — Courses, ca.1977-1983; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Security — Reporting, ca. 1988-1991; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Security — Staff Manual, 1989; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Security — RESTRICTED FILES, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Sophomore Parents Weekend, 1980-1988; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Student Committees and Organizations, 1977-1989; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Student Deposits, 1973-1974; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Student Fellows, 1981-1985; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Student Handbook, 1982-1988; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Student Housing, 1983-1989; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Student Profile, 1975; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Students — Social Life, 1986; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Town Houses, 1971-1983; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Town Students, 1978-1983; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Vassar Student Association — General, 1979-1988; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Vassar Student Association — Budget, 1977-1984; (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Vassar Student Association — Constitution and Grant of Authority, 1969-1985; (1 folder) (Box 6)
- SERIES IV. House Fellow Program
  - House Fellows - Manuals and House Fellow Committee Reports, 1973-1990; (1 folder) (Box 9)
  - House Fellows - Lists, 1951-2002; (1 folder) (Box 9)
  - House Fellows - General, 1951-1961; (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - House Fellows - General — RESTRICTED FILES, 1971-1977; (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - House Fellows - General — RESTRICTED FILES, 1977-1981, 1984-1992, 2002-2003; (13 folders) (Box 8)
  - House Fellows - Reports — RESTRICTED FILES, 1979-1992; (12 folders) (Box 8)
  - Associate House Fellows - RESTRICTED FILES, 1981-1987; (3 folders) (Box 8)